Hello, and thank you for
attending my talk today on Conf
Top Forty-Two, Observability.
I'm going to be looking at what you do
with that observability data after it
has done the job that you want it to do.
It has identified that there is a
problem in the lens of the changing world
that we live in as software engineers.
At PagerDuty, we have a mantra, which is
our own version of the DevOps culture.
Code it, ship it, own it.
You write the code, you ship
it to production, you own what
happened to it afterwards.
How's that gonna change as AI
takes on more and more of the role?
And what will that mean when
things break and the inevitable
happens, somebody has to fix it?
I'm gonna take you to a night
in the very near future.
It's three forty-seven.
Why do these things always happen
in the middle of the night?
I don't know.
But this one, three
forty-seven, not three o'clock.
The pager fires.
We've all been there.
We all know how painful it is.
You drag yourself in
bed, you get downstairs.
It's a SEV 1.
The waning website's
down, revenue's bleeding.
You know the execs are gonna be screaming
about this as soon as they find out.
But there's a difference.
Unlike this year, where you're the
person responsible, in a year's
time, an SRE agent will probably
have had a go at this already.
It will have tried to
work out what's going on.
It might even have tried to fix it if
your company allows you to do it by then.
So you know it's not an easy one.
It's a challenging one.
The easy fix is already gone.
It's not just restart a server.
It's not just roll back the change
that someone deployed half an hour ago.
This is a tough one.
So you open up the code base.
This is a code base you haven't
looked at in the last two years
because you haven't needed to.
The AI agent has been doing all that.
It's been writing all of your code.
For the last year, you haven't
even been merging the PRs.
The PRs have just rolled out.
You have no idea what's
in the code base now.
You haven't even had to deal with
the minor incidents because the
SRE agent's been taking them.
And we hit an uncomfortable question.
The agent can't fix this.
Can you?
We need to start thinking about
what it will take to prepare
for the next era of on-call.
We know the ground is
moving underneath us.
What's changing?
Why does this matter so much now?
Why do we need to think about this?
We also know, though, that we're
not the first to face this change.
Automation is not new.
It has been in a lot of
industries for a long time.
And based on that, we need to start
thinking about how can we build this
future together as software engineers
and for people like myself working
on the c-companies building the
tooling to help you with the incident
response as SaaS providers So why?
Why do we care so much now?
Why is this talk so pertinent?
The ground is moving.
The industry is changing fast.
I think we all know that.
I think anybody who's been in software
development for more than a year or
two will acknowledge that this is
the biggest change they've ever seen.
If you look at CircleCI, they're
reporting huge increase in throughput
and number of runs on main branches,
which means more deployments.
It's skewed, so only the top pro--
companies are seeing the biggest
growth, but that shows that at
least-- for at least some companies,
this is having a significant impact.
And if it's not happening at your
company yet, it will be coming soon.
People will not look at this sort of
cost saving and this sort of speed
increase and not start implementing it
themselves We can also look at GitHub.
Now, there's two-- There's
definitely one factor here.
They're having a significantly
higher throughput, and that's
impacting their downtime.
We can debate whether they've been
overly reliant on coding agents,
and that's caused a second problem.
But we do know the environment is
changing very rapidly As a result,
there will be more incidents.
More code means more incidents.
Fact.
I don't think that's gonna change.
And AI code is gonna
have different incidents.
It's gonna make mistakes.
It's gonna push it out there.
We can have guardrails.
I believe one of the big powers of
AI coding agents is that you can
program them to check everything.
You can give them your platform standards.
You can give them your past incidents
and tell it to look for them.
But it has different failure
modes they will still go through.
So the code it, ship it, own it
mantra that PagerDuty has is breaking.
Coding it.
I can't remember the last time
I sat down and wrote code for
production without the help of AI.
It just doesn't happen anymore.
Ship it.
At the moment at PagerDuty, we are
shipping all of our code manually.
Humans are in the loop.
I say at the moment because we are working
on a future in the near term where we
will allow some code to go straight
to production without human review.
This will increase velocity.
This will decrease familiarity.
What will happen then?
Teams will end up owning more services.
If you don't need to worry about
maintaining a service, why do you keep
the engineer there just for maintenance?
That engineer could be
building a new service.
So your team of ten, ten engineers,
ten services, that's the old rule.
It's gonna be ten engineers, twenty
services, ten engineers, thirty services.
You'll be accountable for systems you
didn't write, you had nothing to do with.
You can't hold all thirty
systems in your head.
You don't know what they're doing,
and you haven't even looked at
them in a long time, but you
will still be the one owning it.
What does that mean?
It means we're entering a third phase
of DevOps Back in the old school
days, we had siloed Dev and Ops.
Developers developed,
ops fixed the problem.
We then moved to the DevOps era.
Anyone who hasn't read The
Phoenix Project, please do.
I reread it recently.
It's amazing how pertinent it still is.
You build it, it helps if you know how
to run it and how to fix it, and if you
don't, if you do have a noc managing
stuff, please talk to them, please learn
from them, because that tight relationship
makes it easier for everybody.
It helps to have a tight feedback loop.
But we're coming to a point
where it's going to change,
and you'll hear two schools of
thought being loudly proclaimed.
You hear one lot saying,
"It's gonna be agent ops.
It's all gonna be done by the agents.
The agents are gonna take over, they're
going to do everything." You have
the other school of thoughts that
say, "Agents are gonna do all of the
writing, all of the deploying, but the
ops is all gonna fall on the humans.
Humans are gonna take this wave of
incidents that are gonna s- fly at
us, and humans are gonna clear it
up." Don't believe in that either.
So we have a challenge coming forward.
We're gonna have code
deployed at AI speed.
Agents are gonna be picking
up the minor incidents.
I do believe agents
will do minor incidents.
There is no reason to have a human
rolling something back, restarting
something, scaling something
up in the middle of the night.
It's far better that I came into my
desk in the morning and got told,
"By the way, last night we had this
problem. We did that. Is that something
you want to make permanent?" Yes.
The trouble is, humans
will lose the training.
We won't be used to dealing with things.
We won't be used to
dealing with incidents.
We won't be used to debugging where
the cost of a debug isn't that much.
Instead, we'll come into the
big one when there's a gnarly,
messy incident and we'll be cold.
We'll have less context, we'll
have less recent practice, and
the stakes will be higher, exactly
when we can least afford it.
The problem is expertise
does not survive on its own.
When automation takes the routine work, we
hit what's called the automation paradox.
The more reliable the automation,
the rustier and rarer the
humans are who can deal with the
situations the automation can't.
So we need to find a way to
practice in a way that is safe
and effective for everybody.
So the engineers are not rusty and cold.
They are aware of how to resolve incidents
when they need to do it, but they haven't
had to make systems riskier to do so.
Fortunately, we're not the first to face
this challenge This, I have to admit, is
one of my favorite movies of all time.
It's fun.
It's great.
I love it.
But it also has a really valuable
lesson for what we're in at the moment.
Why was Top Gun founded?
It was founded because pi-- naval
aviators, get the terminology
right, naval aviators became
overly reliant on missiles.
Swap missiles for automation.
So they lost the ability to dogfight.
Dogfight, manage incidents.
If you become reliant on
something, you lose the ability
to do something you had before.
When the enemy got more advanced,
enemy mo-more advanced, SRE agents,
incidents that they couldn't
resolve got more and more complex,
then naval aviators struggled.
They needed to be trained in a safe
way that actually tested and developed
them Works in the military have a
similar problem in civil aviation.
Initially, everything was manual.
You go back to First World
War, it was a wire and a stick.
You pulled the stick pulled the wire
pulled the flap, the fin, the whatever.
You took off, you landed, you did it all.
Over time, automation came in.
You had autopilots.
Initially, it was just something that
held the stick straight and level.
But as they got better, it's got
to the point where nowadays you
could probably press a button on
the airport here in Lisbon and land
in New York without touching the
controls once and do it very safely.
That's great, apart from the fact pilots
end up sitting there not doing anything,
so they don't know how their planes fly.
They don't know how they feel.
They don't know how to take off.
They don't know how to land.
They're losing the skills that
they need in the very moment
when the autopilot failed.
And the trouble was they lost
those skills, and then autopilots
failed, and there were accidents.
So civil aviation looked at
this and thought, "How can we
make sure this doesn't happen?"
We need to do the same.
If we swap pilot for SRE and autopilot
for agent, we have exactly the same
problem coming in the very near future.
So we need to bring in a fix.
We need to mandate practice and
make sure it happens, which means
we need recurrent simulator time.
For that, we need to know
what our simulator is.
We need to fly manual segments.
How do you practice?
How do you do something?
You don't want an in-incident to
do that, but there are other ways
that you can make sure you're still
practicing the skills you need.
And we need standardized
reviewed scenarios that
actually teach us what we need.
So pilots weren't just sitting in
simulators flying straight and level.
They were practicing based on scenarios
that were specific to the aircraft
that they fly based on observed issues.
We can do-- learn from that.
And that's not the only industry.
NASA is probably one of the
best, if not the best at this.
They are fantastic at training
for everything that's imaginable.
Apollo thirteen got home because they
had amazing simulators and tested.
I've got a mate who works in
search and rescue helicopters.
Every year, he goes to the UK and gets
dropped into a tank like this to see
what happens when he's underwater,
upside down, not sure what's going on,
and he has to get out of the helicopter.
If you ask him about it now, he
goes, "It's great fun. I go swimming
for a couple of days. It's easy."
I have another mate who was in a
helicopter over Greece last summer.
It came down into the
port he was flying over.
He said it was the scariest
thing he's ever had in his life.
Why?
One of them trains every year.
He knows what's happening.
The other one had done no training.
First time he had to deal with it
was when it was actually happening
and his life was in danger.
We can also look closer to home.
Security teams are brilliant at this.
They red team their own s-
own systems all the time.
Let's try and break it.
Let's see what happens if it breaks it.
When they, when you do find a
fault, let's be the ones finding
that fault, and then let's test
against it and train against it.
Get another team trying to resist
the attack, red team, blue team.
We can do the same for our infrastructure
and the same for our reliability.
So we need simulator time too.
We need to build a system
that will allow us to do this.
Re- we need to remember that reactive
incident response isn't training, and
it's gonna be even less tra-- like
training when you lose the easy stuff
and you're just into the scary stuff.
So we need to have practice and
make it routine and deliberate,
scheduled, realistic, and aimed
at the faults that actually hurt.
There's no point training
how to fix a Kubernetes fault
if you do not use Kubernetes
We need to learn from all
incidents, not just the bad ones.
Often, the incidents that you
narrowly avoid give you very good
clues of what could happen in the
incidents that you are yet to come.
If you learn from the ones that you
narrowly avoid, you can often prevent
or mitigate the ones that are about
to come And we need to remember that
readiness becomes a property you maintain.
By keeping your incident responders
sharp, you're in a position to
handle it the next time you get
woken up in the middle of the night.
Unfortunately, though,
practice isn't always enough.
There's always the black swan.
Apollo 13 is an example of this.
They practiced what would happen.
Something bad still happened, but
because they knew how it happened, they
could respond to it I live in Portugal.
Eighteen months ago, we lost the power
outage here because there was a minor
incident that triggered something
else, that triggered something
else, and it took out the country.
Note, this is not a real photo.
This is clearly fake and AI, but it gives
a good example of what was going on.
There is an industry that does
practice, and it still failed.
And something close to my own heart, I
used to work as a nuclear safety engineer.
That's where my interest in
safety and safety cultures and
practice really comes from.
Nuclear is fantastic at practice,
but then Fukushima happens,
you still have a problem.
Even with the best practice, there
will still be incidents, there
will still be black swan events.
But you can make it better,
you can make it easier.
Going back to NASA, look up
the history of the Apollo 11.
They were coming down, the
computer overloaded, but it
overloaded in the right way.
It was well-designed, and Neil
Armstrong had been properly trained
that when it overloaded in that
way and that alarm was going off,
that was an alarm he could ignore.
Practice for the failures and keep calm.
So how do we build our future?
How do we move forward into this together?
We need two things.
We need better tooling,
and we need sharper people.
Better tooling to help us surface
context faster, to use the incident
history to guide our training, and to
have agents that are designed to take
the load, resolve the minor incidents,
and assist us when things go wrong.
We also need sharper people.
They need to work fluently with agents.
They need to know how to
work with the new tooling.
They need to be practiced in
low-stake scenarios, and they
need to know how their tools fail.
Neither alone is enough.
Without the right tools and the
practiced people, it will still fail.
For me, that means building
the right SRE agent.
It needs to be an autopilot, taking
the routine and well understood away
from you so you don't have that toil.
It also needs to be a co-pilot.
It needs to assist on complex incidents
and allow humans who are still in command
to work more efficiently and effectively.
The goal cannot be to replace.
Those two dichotomies I presented earlier,
the autopilot or as agent devs, human
ops, neither of those is gonna be right.
It's gonna be a mix We need to train
effectively based on our incidents,
looking at what's happened, what's gone
wrong, where humans can make a difference.
We need to know how AI struggles.
Use your coding agents regularly.
Use the SRE agents regularly.
Flag where it does well, where it
does badly, where you can practice.
Learn how to use them.
Where are they good?
Where they fail?
What does it look like when they fail?
And expect the black swans.
Get used to dealing with things that
you do not expect because they'll be the
ones that are gonna come through to you
One example of learning your tools
in a black swan event that I find
particularly interesting, though rather
harrowing, is the Aeroflot Flight 593.
Here was a plane cruising on autopilot.
Everything was fine.
The pilot decided to bring
his son to the controls.
Fair enough.
His son, being a typical sixteen-year-old,
decided to pretend it was a
fighter jet, so started yanking the
controls about all over the place.
The plane starts responding.
The pilot panics.
He starts yanking the controls around to
try and get the tr- plane flat and level.
They run out of altitude.
They crash.
Why?
When you yank the controls on
an autopilot, you disengage it.
If the son or the pilot had
just let go of the controls,
it would have re- been saved.
No accident.
The pilot did not know his to- tools.
He did not know that yanking the
controls disables the autopilot That's
the sort of error that will creep in.
We need to know how and when to work
with and work against the tooling we
have provided and what that means.
So what can you do tomorrow morning?
Use agents to read, not just write.
Pick up a random code base from
somewhere else in your organization
and work out how it works.
Get the agent to look at it.
Rehearse in low-stakes scenarios.
We all know them.
Game days, drills, failure Fridays,
chaos monkeys, all these things.
We all know what we should be doing.
It's going to become more and
more important that we do it.
Get used to using your SRE agents in
incidents in low-stakes environments
and learn how your agents fail.
In particular, when they do
it really confidently, their
confidence could be their downfall.
And if you follow that and don't
understand what that confidence looks like
and how to push back and how to challenge
it, you walk down the wrong path.
How do you prepare for the big one?
Red team, game days, chaos engineering,
AI in the loop, incident drills.
It's all the same stuff.
But main thing is, think
about what could bite you.
What happens if your EC spun goes down?
What happens if your
read replica has failed?
What happens if your Kafka
cu- queue shuts down?
Test on those things.
Test on the hard ones.
Prioritize the things that really scare
you and embrace your new ownership model.
Share it between-- share the
workload between you and the agents.
I love the fact I don't have to do
all these minor PRs, bumping packages,
doing this, doing that, whatever.
It's great But use that
time in a constructive way.
Practice other things.
Work on your reliability.
Improve your testing coverage.
And make sure owning it is
becoming a conscious choice.
As you start gaining more and
more services, focus on how you
can learn those services and make
them more and more useful for you.
Code it, ship it, own it.
The agents will code it and ship it.
You, though, will still be the
one who owns it, especially
at oh three forty-seven.
Thank you.